Support Admin Watch on kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
Dukungan Admin Tonton di kissasia.cam atau kisskh.org
=Rise of Her Lady Physician=
=Kebangkitan Dokter Wanita-nya=
=Episode 6=
=Episode 6=
=Prestigious Miss Feng Yin Begs for Mercy=
=Prestigious Miss Feng Yin Begs for Mercy=
A storm is coming.
A storm is coming.
Quickly store the herbs properly
Quickly store the herbs properly
and lock the doors and windows.
and lock the doors and windows.
If any herbs get damp or damaged,
If any herbs get damp or damaged,
I won't go easy on you.
I won't go easy on you.
Aye.
Peluang.
(Rong Zelan,)
(Rong Zelan,)
(today, I'll let you know what price you have to pay)
(today, I'll let you know what price you have to pay)
(for competing with me.)
(for competing with me.)
Attendant Rong.
Attendant Rong.
It occurred to me
It occurred to me
that I left my dress drying in the yard.
that I left my dress drying in the yard.
If it gets drenched,
If it gets drenched,
what will I wear tomorrow?
what will I wear tomorrow?
I need to take it in.
I need to take it in.
Please tidy up the herbs here.
Please tidy up the herbs here.
Okay.
Oke.
Remember to close the doors and windows.
Remember to close the doors and windows.
Oh.
Oh.
You've come at the right time.
You've come at the right time.
It's raining now,
It's raining now,
and my new dress is still hanging in the yard.
and my new dress is still hanging in the yard.
If it gets wet in the rain,
If it gets wet in the rain,
it'll delay my duty tomorrow.
it'll delay my duty tomorrow.
Thankfully, Attendant Rong told me to take it in.
Thankfully, Attendant Rong told me to take it in.
However,
However,
she has to finish the work at the Imperial Pharmacy herself.
she has to finish the work at the Imperial Pharmacy herself.
She must be tired.
She must be tired.
How could she be tired?
How could she be tired?
How tiring could it be to tidy up some herbs?
How tiring could it be to tidy up some herbs?
Attendant Feng,
Petugas Feng,
you're just too kind-hearted.
you're just too kind-hearted.
Exactly.
Tepat.
Don't say that.
Don't say that.
We're all colleagues.
We're all colleagues.
Let's go.
Ayo pergi.
Okay.
Oke.
(I looked through the case records over the years)
(I looked through the case records over the years)
(but didn't find any clues concerning)
(but didn't find any clues concerning)
(the consorts' children.)
(the consorts' children.)
(It seems)
(It seems)
(I need to change my approach.)
(I need to change my approach.)
(Consorts' Cases)
(Consorts' Cases)
It's raining more heavily.
It's raining more heavily.
Fortunately, I closed the doors and windows in time.
Fortunately, I closed the doors and windows in time.
If the heavy rain fell into the Imperial Pharmacy,
If the heavy rain fell into the Imperial Pharmacy,
it'd be a disaster.
it'd be a disaster.
Lord Song.
Lord Song.
Glad to see you again.
Glad to see you again.
This rain came suddenly.
This rain came suddenly.
You have no umbrella.
You have no umbrella.
If you don't mind,
If you don't mind,
we can share an umbrella.
we can share an umbrella.
No need.
No need.
You've finished work,
You've finished work,
so go back and rest early.
so go back and rest early.
Then I'll take my leave.
Then I'll take my leave.
Consort Li is gravely ill
Consort Li is gravely ill
and urgently needs Huoshan Dendrobium.
and urgently needs Huoshan Dendrobium.
Now this batch of medicinal materials has been soaked by rain
Now this batch of medicinal materials has been soaked by rain
and cannot be used.
and cannot be used.
What should we do?
What should we do?
Who was on duty last night?
Who was on duty last night?
It rained so heavily.
It rained so heavily.
I can't believe you left the windows open!
I can't believe you left the windows open!
What on earth are you all doing?
What on earth are you all doing?
Minister Wu, Minister Feng, forgive me.
Minister Wu, Minister Feng, forgive me.
Attendant Rong and I were on duty yesterday.
Attendant Rong and I were on duty yesterday.
I left early to take my dress into my room.
I left early to take my dress into my room.
Before I left, I told her to make sure all windows and doors were closed.
Before I left, I told her to make sure all windows and doors were closed.
Who'd have thought that the windows were wide open this morning?
Who'd have thought that the windows were wide open this morning?
She must've
She must've
made a mistake in a hurry,
made a mistake in a hurry,
so all the medicinal materials got wet.
so all the medicinal materials got wet.
No way.
No way.
How's that possible?
Bagaimana itu mungkin?
Attendant Feng, what do you mean?
Attendant Feng, what do you mean?
Are you saying that the herbs got wet because
Are you saying that the herbs got wet because
I didn't close the windows?
I didn't close the windows?
Last night,
Last night,
Attendant Feng returned to the dormitory with us.
Attendant Feng returned to the dormitory with us.
If not you, who else could it be?
If not you, who else could it be?
Exactly.
Tepat.
We...
We...
W-We went back together.
W-We went back together.
(I knew it.)
(I knew it.)
(Feng Yin made an excuse to leave)
(Feng Yin made an excuse to leave)
(so that she could use the heavy rain to set me up.)
(so that she could use the heavy rain to set me up.)
(Petty tricks.)
(Petty tricks.)
(My backup plan can finally be of use.)
(Rencana cadangan saya akhirnya bisa berguna.)
When I left the Imperial Pharmacy,
Ketika saya meninggalkan Apotek Kekaisaran,
they were all closed,
semuanya sudah ditutup,
and
Dan
Lord Song can testify for me.
Tuan Song dapat bersaksi untukku.
Officer Song,
Petugas Song,
is she telling the truth?
apakah dia mengatakan kebenaran?
Well...
Dengan baik...
Fortunately, I closed the doors and windows in time.
Untungnya, saya menutup pintu dan jendela tepat waktu.
If the heavy rain fell into the Imperial Pharmacy,
Jika hujan deras turun di Apotek Kekaisaran,
it'd be a disaster.
itu akan menjadi bencana.
(No wonder she was so kind, offering to share)
(Tidak heran dia begitu baik hati, menawarkan untuk berbagi)
(an umbrella with me.)
(membawa payung bersamaku.)
(It turns out it was her plan.)
(Ternyata itu rencananya.)
Manure-prepared Licorice.
Akar manis yang diolah dari pupuk kandang.
Minister Wu,
Menteri Wu,
last night, I passed by the Imperial Pharmacy
Tadi malam, aku melewati Apotek Kekaisaran
and saw the doors and windows
dan melihat pintu dan jendela
tightly closed when she left.
tertutup rapat saat dia pergi.
Everything was in place.
Segala sesuatunya sudah pada tempatnya.
Last night, I met you at the Case Room
Tadi malam, aku bertemu denganmu di Ruang Kasus
at a quarter to eight.
pada pukul delapan kurang seperempat.
Did you see Rong Zelan
Apakah kamu melihat Rong Zelan?
leave the Imperial Pharmacy before that?
meninggalkan Apotek Kekaisaran sebelum itu?
Exactly.
Tepat.
At almost eight o'clock,
Hampir pukul delapan,
I left the Case Room.
Saya meninggalkan Ruang Kasus.
When I passed by the Imperial Pharmacy,
Ketika saya melewati Apotek Kekaisaran,
I saw someone push the door open and enter the room.
Saya melihat seseorang mendorong pintu hingga terbuka dan memasuki ruangan.
That figure...
Angka itu...
That figure looked like Attendant Feng.
Sosok itu tampak seperti Petugas Feng.
It was her!
Itu dia!
In other words,
Dengan kata lain,
after I closed the doors and windows and left,
setelah aku menutup pintu dan jendela dan pergi,
you went to open them again secretly, right?
Kau pergi membukanya lagi secara diam-diam, kan?
It wasn't me.
Itu bukan aku.
I did leave my room last night,
Aku meninggalkan kamarku tadi malam,
but I didn't go to the pharmacy
tapi aku tidak pergi ke apotek
but the latrine in the northwest corner.
tetapi jamban di sudut barat laut.
Is that so?
Benarkah begitu?
If I remember correctly,
Jika saya ingat dengan benar,
you usually use the chamber pot.
Anda biasanya menggunakan pispot.
Why would you go to
Kenapa kamu harus pergi ke
the latrine in such heavy rain?
jamban saat hujan deras seperti itu?
Whether I use a chamber pot or a latrine
Apakah saya menggunakan pispot atau jamban
is none of your business.
Itu bukan urusanmu.
Why are you panicking?
Mengapa Anda panik?
Who says I'm panicking?
Siapa bilang saya panik?
Don't slander me.
Jangan memfitnah saya.
Attendant Feng,
Petugas Feng,
when I closed the doors and windows and left the pharmacy,
ketika saya menutup pintu dan jendela dan meninggalkan apotek,
I applied the juniper ointment
Saya mengoleskan salep juniper
I had just prepared on
Saya baru saja mempersiapkan
every door and window.
setiap pintu dan jendela.
The person who went to open them
Orang yang pergi untuk membukanya
hurriedly in the dark
terburu-buru dalam kegelapan
wouldn't have noticed it.
tidak akan menyadarinya.
I'm sure this person's sleeve
Aku yakin lengan orang ini
still has oil stains from the ointment.
masih ada noda minyak dari salepnya.
Oh.
Oh.
Attendant Feng,
Petugas Feng,
why do the brown oil stains on your sleeve
mengapa ada noda minyak berwarna coklat di lengan bajumu?
look so much like my juniper ointment?
mirip sekali dengan salep juniper saya?
Feng Yin,
Fengyin,
now the evidence is clear.
sekarang buktinya jelas.
You deliberately damaged the herbs in the palace
Kamu sengaja merusak tanaman herbal di istana
and framed your colleague.
dan menjebak kolega Anda.
What punishment do you deserve?
Hukuman apa yang pantas kamu terima?
Uncle, help me!
Paman, tolong aku!
Uncle!
Paman!
Help me!
Tolong aku!
Help me, Uncle!
Tolong aku, Paman!
Shut up!
Diam!
You committed a crime.
Anda melakukan kejahatan.
How dare you beg me?
Beraninya kau memohon padaku?
The most important thing now is to find Huoshan Dendrobium.
Hal terpenting sekarang adalah menemukan Huoshan Dendrobium.
Officer Li,
Petugas Li,
is there not a single piece of usable Huoshan Dendrobium left?
apakah tidak ada satu pun potongan Dendrobium Huoshan yang masih bisa digunakan?
Minister Wu, it was all drenched by the rain,
Menteri Wu, semuanya basah kuyup karena hujan,
no stock in the Imperial Medical Bureau.
tidak ada stok di Biro Medis Kekaisaran.
Can we find it outside the palace?
Bisakah kita menemukannya di luar istana?
Lord Wu,
Lord Wu,
Huoshan Dendrobium is a rare material.
Huoshan Dendrobium merupakan material langka.
It's hard to find it quickly outside the palace.
Sulit untuk menemukannya dengan cepat di luar istana.
I'm afraid it's too late.
Saya khawatir sudah terlambat.
What should we do now?
Apa yang harus kita lakukan sekarang?
If Consort Li's condition worsens,
Jika kondisi Selir Li memburuk,
all of our lives combined wouldn't be able to make up for it.
seluruh kehidupan kita digabungkan tidak akan mampu menebusnya.
What should we do?
Apa yang harus kita lakukan?
Minister Wu, Consort Li is extremely painful.
Menteri Wu, Selir Li sangat kesakitan.
Is the medicine ready?
Apakah obatnya sudah siap?
Minister Wu,
Menteri Wu,
I might have a way to restore the effects of the damp herbs.
Saya mungkin punya cara untuk mengembalikan efek ramuan lembab.
- Really? - Yes.
- Benarkah? - Ya.
Then tell us.
Kalau begitu, ceritakan pada kami.
What?
Apa?
Who got the herbs wet?
Siapa yang membasahi tanaman herbal?
If anything happens to Consort Li due to
Jika sesuatu terjadi pada Selir Li karena
delayed use of medicine,
keterlambatan penggunaan obat,
I'll report it to His Majesty, and he'll
Aku akan melaporkannya pada Yang Mulia, dan dia akan
execute the person's entire family.
mengeksekusi seluruh keluarga orang tersebut.
Minister Wu,
Menteri Wu,
if you fail to deliver the medicine
jika Anda gagal memberikan obatnya
and delay the treatment,
dan menunda pengobatan,
all of you will be punished!
kalian semua akan dihukum!
What should we do now?
Apa yang harus kita lakukan sekarang?
Attendant Rong!
Petugas Rong!
Attendant Rong,
Petugas Rong,
are you sure you can solve it?
apakah kamu yakin bisa menyelesaikannya?
Please help me!
Tolong bantu saya!
I apologize to you!
Saya minta maaf pada Anda!
I'm sorry! I'm begging you!
Maafkan aku! Aku mohon padamu!
Please help me!
Tolong bantu saya!
As long as you can solve the problem,
Selama Anda bisa menyelesaikan masalahnya,
I'll do anything for you!
Aku akan melakukan apa saja untukmu!
Please help me!
Tolong bantu saya!
I shouldn't have held a grudge over the pharmacy position!
Saya seharusnya tidak menaruh dendam pada posisi apoteker!
Please help me!
Tolong bantu saya!
I'm sorry!
Saya minta maaf!
Please help me, will you?
Tolong bantu saya.
Will you help me?
Maukah Anda membantu saya?
I don't want to die!
Saya tidak ingin mati!
Minister Wu.
Menteri Wu.
If I restore the effect of the Huoshan Dendrobium,
Jika saya mengembalikan efek Dendrobium Huoshan,
can I be promoted to second-class medical attendant?
dapatkah saya dipromosikan menjadi petugas medis kelas dua?
Can she really solve it?
Bisakah dia benar-benar menyelesaikannya?
If she does, she should be promoted.
Jika demikian, dia seharusnya dipromosikan.
(She stole an officer's clothes and sneaked into the bathhouse,)
(Dia mencuri pakaian seorang petugas dan menyelinap ke pemandian,)
(and now she's asking for a promotion.)
(dan sekarang dia meminta promosi.)
(She is really bold.)
(Dia sungguh berani.)
Lord Wu,
Lord Wu,
saving Consort Li is the top priority.
menyelamatkan Selir Li adalah prioritas utama.
Rong Zelan,
Rong Zelan,
if you really solve the problem,
jika Anda benar-benar menyelesaikan masalahnya,
we'll make an exception to promote you.
kami akan membuat pengecualian untuk mempromosikan Anda.
Thanks, Minister Wu.
Terima kasih, Menteri Wu.
Rong Zelan, I'm warning you.
Rong Zelan, aku peringatkan kau.
If you fail
Jika Anda gagal
and delay Consort Li's treatment,
dan menunda perawatan Selir Li,
you'll be punished according to the rules
kamu akan dihukum sesuai aturan
and expelled from the bureau.
dan dikeluarkan dari biro tersebut.
You must think it through.
Anda harus memikirkannya matang-matang.
Okay, it's a deal.
Oke, sepakat.
I need a lot of sulfur,
Aku butuh banyak belerang,
charcoal,
arang,
and fire starters.
dan pemantik api.
Officer Li, hurry up and get them!
Petugas Li, cepat tangkap mereka!
Aye!
Peluang!
(You're so eager to be promoted.)
(Anda sangat bersemangat untuk dipromosikan.)
(Why exactly did you come here?)
(Apa sebenarnya yang membuatmu datang ke sini?)
It's choking.
Itu menyesakkan.
Will this work?
Apakah ini akan berhasil?
Minister Wu,
Menteri Wu,
it's done. Please take a look.
Sudah selesai. Silakan lihat.
Rong Zelan,
Rong Zelan,
sulfur is very toxic.
sulfur sangat beracun.
A slight mishap can turn it into arsenic.
Kecelakaan kecil dapat mengubahnya menjadi arsenik.
Do you know that?
Tahukah kamu?
Lei Gong's Treatise on Drug Processing
Risalah Lei Gong tentang Pemrosesan Obat
says Dendrobium should avoid fire and toxins.
mengatakan Dendrobium harus menghindari api dan racun.
You are using poison against poison.
Anda menggunakan racun melawan racun.
If anything happens to Consort Li,
Jika sesuatu terjadi pada Selir Li,
can you afford the consequences?
bisakah kamu menanggung akibatnya?
Zelan,
Bagaimana,
is there any basis
apakah ada dasar
for the method you used?
untuk metode yang Anda gunakan?
Minister Wu,
Menteri Wu,
sulfur fumigation
fumigasi belerang
can effectively remove moisture from herbs.
dapat secara efektif menghilangkan kelembapan dari tanaman herbal.
If Huoshan Dendrobium gets damp,
Jika Dendrobium Hushan menjadi lembab,
it'll not only reduce its effects
itu tidak hanya akan mengurangi dampaknya
but also cause mold spots.
tetapi juga menyebabkan timbulnya bercak jamur.
The gas produced by burning sulfur
Gas yang dihasilkan dari pembakaran belerang
can effectively remove mold spots
dapat menghilangkan noda jamur secara efektif
and ensure the quality.
dan memastikan kualitasnya.
What's more, charcoal
Terlebih lagi, arang
can absorb the sulfur remaining on the herbs
dapat menyerap sisa sulfur pada tanaman herbal
so that it won't make them toxic.
sehingga tidak membuatnya beracun.
Young as you are,
Meski kamu masih muda,
you're so skilled and knowledgeable.
Anda sangat terampil dan berpengetahuan.
May I ask
Bolehkah saya bertanya?
where you learned this method?
dimana Anda mempelajari metode ini?
I've studied medicine
Saya telah mempelajari ilmu kedokteran
for a decade and offered monthly free clinics to the people
selama satu dekade dan menawarkan klinik gratis bulanan kepada masyarakat
to gain experience
untuk mendapatkan pengalaman
and refine my skills.
dan mengasah keterampilan saya.
I learned this method from an itinerant physician
Saya mempelajari metode ini dari seorang dokter keliling
I met by chance.
Saya bertemu secara kebetulan.
I see.
Jadi begitu.
It seems I'm so ignorant
Sepertinya aku sangat bodoh
that I've never seen such an ingenious method.
bahwa saya belum pernah melihat metode yang begitu cerdik.
How can you ensure that there is no sulfur poison at all?
Bagaimana Anda dapat memastikan tidak ada racun sulfur sama sekali?
Attendant Feng.
Petugas Feng.
This is the Imperial Medical Bureau.
Ini adalah Biro Medis Kekaisaran.
We have all the outstanding physicians in our country.
Kita memiliki semua dokter yang luar biasa di negara kita.
It's not difficult
Itu tidak sulit
to test its toxicity, is it?
untuk menguji toksisitasnya, bukan?
I'm afraid I'll be promoted
Aku takut aku akan dipromosikan
to second-class attendant first.
ke petugas kelas dua terlebih dahulu.